土星上的胜利
视频、英文字幕版权：NASA JPL
渣翻中字/时间轴：PolestarX
如果让人描绘一幅代表行星的图画，
Ask someone to draw a picture of a planet,
结果很可能就是这个：
and odds are it will be this one.
太阳系中的第六颗行星，
It is the sixth planet out from the sun
也是第二大的行星
and the second-largest in our solar system.
这 就是土星
It is, of course, Saturn,
一个被宏伟光环所围绕的世界
a world encircled not only in majestic rings
而且拥有数量众多的卫星
but in an array of moons that have been likened
如同一个太阳系的缩影
to a solar system in miniature.
1997年，一项去往土星的国际任务拉开序幕
In 1997, an international mission was launched to Saturn
这将是首次
that would, for the first time,
试图把航天器送入土星轨道
attempt to place an orbiting spacecraft around the planet
还要将探测器降落外太阳系的卫星上
and land a probe on a moon in the outer solar system.
但这项任务
But this was a mission that had to
困难重重
fight its way to the launch pad.
我们的项目
- [Lew] We're going to have to operate
面临非常严格的资金限制，
under a very strict fund ceiling,
此项法案会由国会强制实施
one that is imposed by Congress.
因此需要一种与之前截然不同的方式
- This will require doing business
来进行这项任务
in a drastically different way than we've done before.
[Bob]耗费大量时间，经过多轮谈判
- [Bob] It took a lotta time, a lotta negotiating,
做出很多妥协后才得以付诸实行
a lot of compromises to make that work.
第一次看到
- [Julie] The first time I saw the spacecraft together
没有被遮布覆盖的飞船时，
when we stacked without the blankets, we were just,
我们都瞠目结舌
we were without words standing out there.
去土星的旅程
- [Narrator] The journey to Saturn
需要七年之久，
would take seven long years,
但决定它能否成功被土星捕获从而进入轨道的关键时间
but the success, or failure, of being captured into orbit
只有短短的三个小时
depended on what would happen during just three hours.
[Charles]祈祷引擎最好能点火，
- [Charles] The engine better fire,
否则我们将以一次飞掠告终
otherwise we'll end with a flyby.
-收到
- Copy.
DCS故障保护
DCS Fault Protection.
[Linda]作为一名光环科学家，
- [Linda] I think as a ring scientist,
我最担心的是
my greatest concern was really crossing
飞船通过F环和G环间隙的时刻
through that gap in the F and G rings.
只要一个弹珠大小的颗粒
It would only have taken one marble sized particle
撞上飞船的关键位置
in the wrong place in the spacecraft
大概任务就宣告结束了
to perhaps have ended the mission.
所以入夜时，我躺在床上想着：
- [Man] So I would lie in bed at night and think about
我们还应该做哪些测试？
what other tests should we do?
我还应该问什么问题？
What other question should I be asking?
还需要查出哪些未完成的事项？
What should we be poking out here that we haven't done yet?
[Julie]我们追查一切可能出错的事情
- [Julie] We chased everything that could go wrong
这非常困难
down the rabbit hole.
我们考虑每一种情况，如果这里出了问题，
We went down every path of, if this goes wrong,
我们该怎么办？
what do we do?
如果那里又出现问题，我们该怎么办？
If that goes wrong, what do we do?
[Earl]这就是其中的一个关键时刻
- [Earl] And this was one of those moments
要么成功进入轨道
where you're either in orbit
要么数十亿美元打了水漂
or you're a billion dollar flyby.
[Todd]距抵达最接近点
- [Todd] Closest approach is just a little over
还有两分钟出头
two minutes away.
预测今天的气温为-226华氏度，
Predicted temps today, -226 degrees Fahrenheit,
风速每小时1100英里
winds of 1100 miles per hour.
那里的飓风和地球一样大
Hurricanes the size of the Earth.
最好把卡西尼号的舱门关上
Cassini would do well to batten down the hatches.
土星上的胜利 第一部分：JPL 和太空时代
无奈之举*
土星曾经只是一个
- [Narrator] Saturn was once but a single
夜空中的亮点，
bright point of light in the night sky,
但在1610年，伽利略通过他的望远镜
but in 1610 Galileo peered through his telescope
看到了一些别的东西
and saw something else.
他认为在这个星球的两边，
On either side of the planet,
可能存在卫星
he thought there might be moons.
两年后，伽利略再次观测
Two years later, Galileo looked again.
令他吃惊的是，这两个物体不见了
To his astonishment, the two objects had disappeared.
又过了两年，伽利略再次
Another two years passed and Galileo again
将望远镜对准土星
trained his telescope on Saturn.
令人费解的凸出部分再次出现
The puzzling bulges had returned.
这张图显示了伽利略
This drawing shows how close Galileo came
距离谜题的答案有多近，
to solving the riddle,
但他在不知道真相的情况下与世长辞
but he went to his grave without ever knowing the answer.
半个世纪之后，荷兰科学家
A half century would pass before the Dutch scientist
克里斯蒂安·惠更斯意识到这些凸起是圆环
Christiaan Huygens realized the bulges were rings.
至于它们时隐时现，
As for their appearing and disappearing,
惠更斯意识到这是由土星倾斜引起的
Huygens realized that was caused by Saturn's tilting.
像地球一样，土星在其轴线上轻微地来回摆动
Like Earth, Saturn gently rocks back and forth on its axis.
在黎明时分从地球上观测光环时，
And when the rings are viewed from Earth at dawn,
它们几乎不可见
they all but disappear.
随着时间的推移，土星逐渐进入我们的视野，
As time passed, Saturn came into closer focus,
1979年，NASA 的先驱者11号宇宙飞船
and in 1979, NASA's Pioneer 11 spacecraft
为全世界带来了首次近距离的观测——
gave the world the first closeup look
土星和它的光环
at the planet and its rings.
昨天下午我们收到了几张照片
- We received several pictures yesterday afternoon
今晚，我们就快速浏览一遍
and evening, and we'd like to run through some of those now.
这就是那张
This is the one that came in here
昨天下午三点左右传来的照片
at about three o'clock yesterday afternoon.
这是我们目前拍到的
This is by far the most spectacular picture
最壮观的一幅画面
that we have so far.
这就是原始数据
This is raw data.
没有经过任何处理
It has not been processed in any way.
我们可以看到这颗巨大的带环行星，当然，
We can see the big banded planet and, of course,
在这张图片中，环状系统非常引人注目
the ring system is very prominent in this picture.
同样显眼的是土星最大的卫星土卫六（泰坦），
Also prominent is Saturn's largest moon, Titan,
它出现在右上角
in the upper right-hand corner.
此后不久，两架旅行者号飞掠过去，
- [Narrator] The two Voyager flybys soon followed,
得到了更加迷人的景色和发现
offering even more captivating views and discoveries.
这些任务的成果让科学家们
What these missions found left scientists
强烈要求再探土星，这次不仅仅是飞过
clamoring to go again, and not just to pass by,
而是在土星停留
but to stay.
一份蓝图，甚至一些备件
A blueprint and even some spare parts
已经为此准备好了
for just such an adventure already existed.
NASA 此前的伽利略任务，
NASA's Galileo mission,
向木星发射了一个轨道飞行器和一个探测器
that sent an orbiter and a probe to Jupiter.
欧洲和美国的支持者
Advocates in Europe and the United States
主张一个前往土星的类似任务，
argued for a similar mission destined for Saturn,
并使之成为一个国际合作项目
one composed of an international consortium.
没有人知道
How such a project with all its complexities
如此复杂的项目是否能成功
could be done, no one really knew.
仅划分角色、职责，特别是出资，
Sorting out roles, responsibilities, and especially funding,
就用了快十年时间
took the better part of a decade.
欧洲航天局提出要建造探测器，
The European Space Agency offered to build the probe,
名为惠更斯，负责降落到土卫六
named Huygens, to land on Saturn's moon Titan.
意大利航天局将建造主天线
The Italian Space Agency would build the main antenna
以及通信系统
and communication system.
探测器的推进器和主发动机
The spacecraft thrusters and the main engines
将由美国商业航天公司提供
would be provided by US commercial space companies.
NASA JPL
And NASA's Jet Propulsion Laboratory signed on
负责建造和控制飞船卡西尼号，
to build and fly the spacecraft,
其为纪念17世纪
to be named in honor of the 17th century
天文学家乔瓦尼·卡西尼而得名
astronomer Giovanni Cassini.
JPL 还负责计划的统筹管理
JPL would also provide overall management of the mission.
总共有19个国家提供硬件设备，
In total, 19 countries would provide hardware,
而参与该计划的科学家将来自26个国家
while scientists would come from 26 nations.
早上好
- Good morning.
欢迎大家来到JPL，
I wanna welcome all of you to JPL,
一起开启
and at the beginning of what is gonna be clearly
这项无疑是激动人心的任务
a very exciting mission.
我知道你们很多人都有...
I know that a lot of you have a...
这是卡西尼-惠更斯号的科学家和工程师们的
- [Narrator] This is the first gathering
第一次聚会，
of Cassini Huygens scientists and engineers,
目标是将这种错综复杂的合作伙伴关系
their goal to transform this complex partnership
转变为一个正常运作的团队
into a functioning team.
我们的国会对这个计划颇有微词
- Our Congress has had some agony over the program.
暂时只有任务的卡西尼部分
For a time it looked as though only Cassini
会获得批准
would be approved.
房间里遍布愁云
- [Narrator] There are layers of unease in the room.
欧洲人想知道他们是否
The Europeans want to know that they'll be
会被平等对待
treated as equal partners.
还有人担心美国是否可靠，
And there are also concerns about US reliability,
尤其是考虑到 NASA 最近退出了
given that NASA has recently dropped out
另一个合作项目
of another partnership.
我们的计划
- We're going to have to operate
被国会严格限制了资金上限，
under a very strict fund ceiling,
除此之外还有一个必须遵守的日程表
one that is imposed by Congress and an unyielding schedule.
我们都面临着巨大的挑战-
And we all have great challenges-
NASA 已经发出警告
- [Narrator] NASA has already warned
如果项目超出预算
that the mission will be canceled
任务就会被取消
if the project strays over its budget.
所有的目光都集中在卡西尼号的第一个项目经理身上：
All eyes are on Cassini's first program manager,
约翰·卡萨尼，他已经提出
John Casani, who has already spoken of eliminating
要削减一些科学仪器
some of the science instruments.
真的很欢迎大家
- Seriously like to welcome everybody.
很高兴来到这里
Nice to be here.
很多老朋友和新面孔，
A lot of old friends, a lot of new faces,
希望在经历项目之前*
which I hope we'll be friends before we're through
我们能成为朋友
with this process.
如果你还不认识我，
But those of you who don't know me,
在接下来的几年里会熟悉起来的
will find out a lot in the next couple of years.
这次的任务
This will require doing business in a fairly drastically
和以前截然不同
different way than we've done before.
我们都必须为之奋斗，
We are all gonna have to strive for,
整个过程需要不断探索，
as we go through this process, is a continual search,
正如我的老朋友李先生常说的，
as my old friend Gentry Lee used to like to say,
这个方案是无奈之举
for the least unacceptable solution.
必然要做出妥协
There are gonna have to be compromises.
我们想要合作
We wanna work with you.
这不是科学家们希望听到的
- [Narrator] This was not what scientists had hoped to hear.
我认为这极大地削减了
- I think this is a very severe degrade
这次任务的探索能力
in the capabilities of this mission.
只有在做完所有这些事之后
- What we did was we did all of these things
才能真正地开展实际的计划
to finally get down to something that we could afford.
在我看来，这样做是非常不明智的
- That sounds to me like a very unwise thing to do.
我的意思是，这项任务的实质是传回探测数据
I mean, the essence of this mission is to get data back.
科学家的诉求
- [Narrator] The friction between what scientists want
与实际工程实现之间的争执
and what engineers can do will be a theme
将贯穿整个任务周期
running throughout the lifetime of the mission.
接下来，我们将决定卡西尼号上
So, we'll be deciding which of Cassini's
12种科学仪器
12 different science instruments will have priority
的使用时间优先级
at any given time.
首先陈述提议的是
First up to plead his case is the head
科学雷达团队的领导查尔斯·埃拉奇
of the science radar team, Charles Elachi.
早上好
- Good morning.
我从丹尼斯那里了解到第一位发言人
I understand from Dennis that the first speaker
的所有要求都被批准了
gets everything he asks for.
雷达有优点也有缺点
There is a good thing and a bad thing about the radar.
优点是，对于每一条土星轨道，
The good thing is that for every Saturn orbit,
我们只需要操作一个小时
we need to operate only for one hour.
剩下的时间都归你们，我们只占用一小时
You can have all the rest of the time, but one hour.
坏消息是当我们打开雷达时，
The bad thing is that when we turn it on,
飞船上的光源会变暗，
the lights* on the spacecraft will dim,
你懂的，亮度会下降
you know, it'll go down.
代表成像团队发言的是
- [Narrator] Representing the needs of the imaging team
它的领导人卡罗琳·波科
is its leader, Carolyn Porco.
...比这个低的标准
- Rates which are lower than that.
我们知道
After all, we know what it will take
对于那些规划好的土星拍摄目标
to image the objects at Saturn,
我们清楚它们的位置
that we know are there.
我主要担心那些计划之外的场景
My question is, what is it that's there that we don't know
因此希望有一个非常稳定的平台
and we want to have a very stable platform
能够进行长时间曝光
and be able to do long exposures.
这些都是让科学家们
These are issues that ring scientists
彻夜难眠的问题
stay up late at night worrying about.
我们比计划进度落后了一些
- We are running a bit behind schedule
所以跳过喝咖啡的休息时间，
so we shall skip the coffee break,
但我们仍然会提供咖啡
but there is still coffee for those who can't survive*.
一个接一个，
- [Narrator] One after another,
科学团队走上讲台说明诉求
the science teams take to the podium to make their pitches
有时也表达他们的不满
and at times to express their displeasure.
我们是一个较小的团队，
- Okay, this is one of the smaller teams,
管理其中一个较小的仪器（磁强计，Magnetometer），
and I suppose one of the smaller instruments,
但它能派上大用场
although perhaps not as small as the project might like.
所以我想说的是
I'm afraid I have to say that we have to have
我们必须获得在行星环境下
an instrument that performs best
性能最好的仪器
within the planetary environment.
所以这件事并不像有些人
So life is not as simple as perhaps
从表面看上去的那么简单
some people have seen it.
我们在这里遇到的另一个挑战
- The other challenge that we've had here
在过去的几个月里，人们认识到
is a recognition over the past few months that the...
为了解决这些冲突，
- [Narrator] Hoping to resolve these conflicts,
卡萨尼提出了一个意想不到的计划
Casani offers up an unexpected plan
用来更好地约束科学家
to put the scientists more in control.
我们鼓励各位
- We need to incentivize you to do the best job
在确认计划时
of making the best estimates of what it's gonna cost
对它的成本做出最准确的估计
at the time of confirmation.
卡萨尼不是发号施令
Instead of having decisions made from the top down,
而是建议建立一个交易系统
Casani proposes establishing a trading system.
每个科学团队都将分到一定数额的资金，
Each science team will be given a defined amount of money,
重量、能耗和数据速率指标
mass, power and data rates.
如果之后他们需要更多，
If later they need more of anything,
就必须与其他团队合作
they will have to work with the other teams
以解决他们的问题
to solve their problem.
科学家们接受了这种特别的以物换物系统
The scientists agree to this unusual bartering system.
这是第一个重要步骤
It is the first major step in building
用以建设一支运作良好的国际团队
a functioning international team.
有问题吗？
- Any questions?
好的，丹尼斯，谢谢你
All right, Dennis, thank you.
系统就绪
到1997年秋天，
- [Narrator] By the fall of 1997,
曾经的图纸
what had once been just blueprints
变为了现实
are now real pieces of hardware.
在过去的六年中，
For over the last six years,
另一项曾经被努力挽留的任务，
the mission has managed to survive being canceled,
也就是用 NASA 飞船
something another NASA spacecraft
与彗星会合小行星飞掠计划（CRAF），
meant to rendezvous with a comet and an asteroid,
最终还是被取消了
was unable to do.
NASA 新规划的一部分
This was part of a new NASA strategy to cut back
就是缩减大型昂贵航天器的预算
on large and expensive spacecraft.
而卡西尼号的尺寸无法掩饰：
*And there was no disguising Cassini's size.
至今为止，
It remains, to this day,
它还是美国有史以来建造的最大的星际飞船
the largest US interplanetary spacecraft ever built.
竖立时有三层楼高，
Standing three stories tall, when fully loaded,
满载时将重达1.25万磅（5.6 吨）
it will weigh 12 and a half thousand pounds.
第一次看没有被遮布掩盖的，
- The first time I saw the spacecraft together,
组装完成的飞船时，
when we stacked without the blankets,
我当时一定在游客走廊上站了有30分钟
I must have stood in the visitor gallery for 30 minutes.
我不知道怎么形容它
And it's... I don't know how to describe it.
你知道，它不再属于你了
It's not yours anymore, you know.
尽管我对每一个组件都很熟悉
Even though I had been intimate with each piece
一个接一个地
and part of that spacecraft and put it together
亲手把飞船组装起来，
wire by wire and in part by part,
但看到它成为一个整体时还是感到不可思议
to watch it come together as a whole entity was incredible.
我们站在那，静默无言
We were without words standing out there.
我们偶尔会在这里工作
- Every now and then we'll be working in here
就会想，哇，这将飞往土星
and you'll think, wow, this is going to Saturn
这个探测器将降落在泰坦上
and this probe is gonna land on Titan.
那是我们从未去过的地方
And this is going somewhere where we've never
想到这些，就会心潮澎湃
seen things before and you get goosebumps from it.
宇宙飞船的设计
- [Narrator] The spacecraft has been designed
优先考虑了冗余
with redundancy as a priority.
每个关键系统都有一个相同的备份
Each critical system has an identical backup.
其先进的软件将允许航天器
And its advanced software will allow the spacecraft
在某些时候自主飞行，
at times to fly on its own,
甚至自我修复电脑故障
and even self-repair computer glitches.
卡西尼号内部有大约22000个线缆连接
In Cassini's interior are some 22,000 wire connections
还有超过7英里的电缆
and more than seven miles of cabling.
严格来说，我是一名工程助理，
- I'm technically an engineering assistant,
我的工作是为宇宙飞船布线
and what I do is cabling for the spacecraft
我已经做了20年了
and I've been doing it for 20 years.
我们机械团队的一个很大优点是
One of the really positive points about our mechanical team
就是绝不放弃
is that they never say no.
团队似乎从不疲倦
They never seem to tire.
总是很积极
They're always up.
我们已经做到最好了
(chuckles) I don't think we could ask for a better team.
*
最后一项装配任务包括
- [Narrator] One of the last assembly tasks
用毯子盖住这个裸露的飞船
is to cover this bare spacecraft with blankets.
使用的机器常用于手工精细剪裁
Using machines more often used for fine tailoring
而非工业用途，
than engineering,
用裁切过的反光材料在任务早期
this reflective material is cut to protect the spacecraft
在飞向太阳时保护航天器
early in the mission, when it flies toward the sun.
这种黑色织物的效果正好相反，
This black fabric will do the opposite,
在土星吸收和保持热量，
absorbing and retaining heat out at Saturn,
那里的阳光强度只有地球的1%
where sunlight is only 1% the strength found at Earth.
这些保护层还将屏蔽那些
The layers will also provide shielding
微小流星体
from micro meteoroids,
以及细小的灰尘颗粒
tiny particles of dust that could damage
它们可能会损害宇宙飞船的电子设备
the spacecraft's electronics.
这是一项乏味的工作，
This is tedious work,
切割、缝合和装配
cutting, stitching and fitting hundreds
大量单独定制的工件
of individually measured pieces.
考虑到这个“太空被子”非常精巧复杂，
It is a job made even more challenging
这项工作会更具挑战性
knowing that this intricate space quilt,
就像卡西尼号的所有主要部件一样，
like all of Cassini's major components,
必须拆卸才能运抵佛罗里达州，
will have to be unmounted for shipping to Florida,
所有的东西都要在那里重新组装
where everything will be reassembled again.
我们在卡西尼号上遇到的问题
- We have had less problem with this
比我记得的任何其他飞船上都要少
than I can remember having on any other spacecraft.
难以置信
*It's almost scary.
它真漂亮啊
It's just beautiful.
没有碰上大麻烦
No problems.
最多只是些小问题
No major problems anyway.
依据卡西尼号的蓝图
- [Narrator] While transforming Cassini from a blueprint
建造出一艘真正的宇宙飞船的过程非常顺利，
into a real spacecraft had gone exceptionally well,
但敲定最终设计的过程却备受折磨
getting to the final design had been torturous.
遭遇预算削减，该项目被迫
Facing budget cuts, the project was forced
做出另一个无奈之举
to make another least unacceptable decision*.
为了不减少科学仪器，
Instead of dropping science instruments,
飞船的尺寸被缩小，
the spacecraft itself was scaled back by eliminating
取消了扫描平台，
the scan platform,
这个平台是一种转盘
a kind of turntable required by some instruments
搭载某些需要移动的仪器
needing motion.
没有了平台，
Without the platform, the entire spacecraft
探测器需要通过整体旋转来瞄准目标，
will have to rotate to aim at targets,
这减少了观测时间
resulting also in less observation time.
但所有的科学仪器都保留了下来
But all of the science instruments have survived.
卡西尼-惠更斯号
Operations are now almost complete
即将发射
for the launch of Cassini Huygens.
发射台上是空军的
Already on the launch pad is the Air Force's
大力神4号B型运载火箭
heavy lifting Titan 4B
卡西尼号和探测器已经重新组装
Cassini and the probe have been reassembled.
最后一道程序包括
One of the last procedures involves
将其电源加装到航天器上，
loading onto the spacecraft its power supply,
72磅钚被封装在
72 pounds of plutonium encased in
放射性同位素热电发电机中，
what are called radio isotope thermoelectric generators,
或者缩写为 RTG
or mercifully called for short RTGs.
RTG 在以前的任务中使用过，
RTGs have been used on previous missions,
但是最近的核电站事故
but recent nuclear power plant accidents
还有挑战者号航天飞机的失利
and the loss of the Space Shuttle Challenger
加剧了公众对发射事故
have heightened public fears of a launch accident
会扩散核物质碎片的恐惧
spreading nuclear debris.
为了终止发射，
Hoping to stop the launch,
反核组织提起诉讼，向白宫请愿，
anti-nuclear groups file lawsuits, petition the White House,
并在肯尼迪航天中心举行示威
and hold demonstrations at the Kennedy Space Center.
这是最后的机会在公开对话中向大家保证
- Since this is the last  to ensure the public
这次不会发生事故
that everything is going to be all right,
你能最后一次
could you do that one last time
用最好的论据去说服，
and use your best argument to persuade,
你的反对者们吗
perhaps, some of your opponents?
RTG的设计考虑到了发生事故的情况
- RTGs were designed for accident conditions.
我们设计并测试，
We've designed them, we've tested them,
已经进行分析，而且经历过了
we've analyzed for it, we've gone through
一个非常漫长的审查过程
a very lengthy review process.
事实上，这些都是非常安全的
And in fact, these are very safe to use.
对公众没有风险，
There's not a risk to the public,
即使发生事故也是如此
even if there is an accident.
你们能确认你们对这次任务的信心吗
- Would you all confirm your faith in this mission
告诉我们有多少你的家庭成员，孩子，
by telling us how many family members, kids,
还有孙子孙女一起看这次发布会？
and grandkids you have here watching this launch with you?
我在这里有30个家庭成员，
- Well, I have 30 members of my family here right now,
包括我的两个孙女
including my two granddaughters.
可能还将有更多孩子即将出世
There's more on the way.
我不知道我是否会有更多的孙子孙女，
I don't know if I have more grandchildren on the way,
但确实会有更多的家庭成员
but I have more family on the way*.
现实是，当下
The reality is there's no technology on the horizon
以及在可预见的将来
that has the promise to be available
没有任何其他技术可以确保
in the foreseeable future at all
在外太空供能
that could be used for feigning power, way in outer space,
实际上那里的阳光非常少
where there is effectively very little sunlight.
在土星，仅为地球上的1%
At Saturn, we've got a 1% of what we have here on Earth.
我们知道卡西尼号是安全的
We know Cassini is safe.
发电机的设计是为了在各种环境中保持稳定
The generator is designed to be robust in the environments.
我们不完全依赖于成功的情况
We do not rely on success.
而是使其可以与环境共存
We make it compatible with the environments
事故可能发生，但它是安全的
that might be generated and it's safe.*
我邀请了所有我爱的人参加这次发射
I invited everyone I love to the launch.
会有放出消息吗
- [Man] Will there be information
关于这次发射是否成功
on the success of this launch too?
当然
- Absolutley.
你可以看到我们将会带着香槟庆祝
You can find us with a bottle of champagne some place.
FLC，325和326完成
- [Man] FLC, we have 325 and 326 complete.
收到
Roger.
EA和LCC 327和328准时
- [Man] EA and LCC 327 and 328 on time.
收到
Roger.
LCC，收到
- [Woman] LCC, roger.
空军发射控制员
- [Man] The Air Force launch controller
已经给了一个明确的发射指示
has given a clear to launch.
我们必须离开这个范围才能
We've got to go from the range
继续进行倒计时
to proceed with the countdown.
发射序列启动
- [Woman] Launch sequence started.
倒计时 10 秒，
- [Man] T minus 10,
九
nine,
八
eight,
七
seven,
六
six,
五
five,
四
four,
三
three,
二
two,
一
one,
卡西尼号飞船已经发射
and liftoff of the Cassini spacecraft
踏上前往土星的数十亿英里的征程
on a billion mile trek to Saturn.
俯仰控制运行中
Pitch program is in.
我们已经清理了发射架
- [Man] We have cleared the tower*
卡西尼号飞船正在前往土星的途中
and the Cassini spacecraft is on its way to Saturn.
发射后 20 秒
T+20 seconds.
所有系统正常
All systems are go.
准备进行固体火箭助推器分离
Standing by for solid rocket booster separation.
固体火箭推进器分离
And the solid rocket boosters have been jettisoned.
项目149和150
- [Man] Item 149 and 150.
所有系统正常
- [Man] All systems go.
“闲置的飞船是恶魔们的游乐场”
所有CAS核心站，运行工程师，
- [Man] All CAS core stations, ops engineer,
运载火箭报告载荷整流罩已经分离
launch vehicle reports payload fairing jettisoned.
-这次发射完美达成预期
- This launch was, for all practical purposes, perfect.
非常精准
It was just right on target.
往常预期在
And the navigation corrections that we normally,
这类发射任务中需要导航校准
routinely expect to have to make
而这次需要的校正非常小
for these kinds of launches was very small.
这是一次极其出色的发射
It was an exceptionally good launch.
尽管这次发射很出色，
- [Narrator] But the launch, as good as it was,
但还是不足以将卡西尼号直接送到土星
was not powerful enough to send Cassini directly to Saturn.
为了实现这一目标，任务设计师们早就
To get there, mission designers had long before
利用大自然的力量规划了一条飞行路线
devised a flight path, using mother nature
通过掠过行星获得额外的速度，
to gain extra boosts of speed by flying by planets,
也被称为引力弹弓（重力助推）
what are called gravity assists.
卡西尼号的飞行路线需要在金星上进行两次向内转弯，
Cassini's route required two inward swing bys at Venus,
然后回到地球，之后向外飞到木星，
next back to Earth, then outward to Jupiter,
最后才到土星
and finally on to Saturn.
总的来说，一次超过20亿英里的旅程，
In all, a journey of over 2 billion miles,
持续近七年
lasting nearly seven years.
第一次飞到金星时，
During the first Venus encounter,
卡西尼号低空掠过行星表面，
Cassini grazed just above the planet's surface,
速度增加每小时16000英里
gaining an extra 16,000 miles per hour of speed.
卡西尼号飞船已经进入太空，
- The Cassini spacecraft has now been in space,
飞行了八个多月
in flight, for a little over eight months.
航天器的性能
And the performance of the spacecraft has been
完美无瑕
essentially flawless.
通常在复杂度如此之高的航天器上，
Typically on spacecraft like this, of this complexity,
会遇到各种各样的问题，
there are issues, complications of one sort or another,
这时我们必须与我们的一些陆基部门
that we have to work with some of our ground-based
共同指挥
command capability.
对于卡西尼号飞船来说，这根本就不需要
For the Cassini spacecraft, this just hasn't happened.
这是一艘了不起的宇宙飞船
It's a remarkable spacecraft.
确实如此，
- [Narrator] True enough,
但卡西尼号还不是一个完整的航天器
but Cassini is not yet a fully complete spacecraft.
发射时，有足够多的飞控软件
- We had enough flight software on board at launch
负责驾驶飞船，操控，导航，
to be able to fly the spacecraft, operate it, navigate it,
除此之外就没有别的软件了
and not a whole lot more than that.
-发射后，我们有七年的时间
- When we launched, we had seven years
为了到达土星，我们实际上
to get to Saturn and we actually
在飞行中两次完全改写了计算机系统
completely changed out the computer system twice in flight.
我们先使用旧软件
We would take the old computer software
然后在备份计算机中加载新软件，
and then load up the new software in the backup computer,
观察一段时间，确保新软件稳定
watch it for a while, make sure it was stable.
然后我们交换两者
And then we would swap and make the backup
并备份主计算机
the prime computer.
确保稳定工作
Make sure it was stable.
当工程师们编写卡西尼号的软件时
- [Narrator] As engineers worked on completing
科学家们则开始游说
Cassini's software, scientists started lobbying
争取他们的仪器使用时间配额
to begin using their instruments
这远远地超前于计划的时间表
far ahead of the agreed upon schedule.
这里有幅图片
- The cartoon.
你得来看看它
You gotta see the cartoon.
就能知道来龙去脉
You gotta see the whole thing.
“闲置的宇宙飞船是魔鬼的游乐场”
So the idle spacecraft is the devil's playground.
起初的三年中，
For the first three years,
我们本无须做任何事
we weren't supposed to do anything.
就当是飞了一块石头出去
We were supposed to fly a rock.
我们本来打算按此执行，
And we were just gonna go take this,
对飞船做一些工程上的校正，
take the spacecraft, correct it engineering wise,
只是飞过几次金星和地球，
fly it by Venus, a couple of times by Earth,
我们真的不打算在此期间做太多的科学研究
and we really weren't gonna do much science.
然后科学家们说，
And here were the scientists saying,
现在有一艘很棒的飞船，
"You've got this great spacecraft,
一切都运行良好，你不必检查..
everything's working on it, you don't have to check...
不需要再检查隔热
You know, you don't have to redo your thermal.*
不用重复检查了
You don't have to redo this.
还是开始科学研究吧
Let's do science."
所以有一次我进来的时候，门上挂着这个
And so I came in one day and this was on my door.
闲置的宇宙飞船是魔鬼的游乐场
The idle spacecraft is the devil's playground.
我发誓肯定是某一位科学家*
I swore for years that one of the scientists
把它挂在门上
had put that on my door.
后来发现就是我的领导干的*
It was my boss.
他把这张图片贴在我的门上
He put that on my door.
大部分情况下，
- [Narrator] For the most part,
团队会迁就科学家们
the scientists were accommodated,
但安全飞过地球
but the project's priority was first
是项目的首要任务
getting safely past the Earth,
1999年夏天，
which occurred in the summer of 1999,
地球又使卡西尼号的速度增加了每小时12000英里
giving Cassini another 12,000 miles per hour of speed.
接下来的关键是通过火星轨道
The next milestones were passing beyond the orbit of Mars
以及小行星带的区域
and the region of the asteroid belt.
然后是木星
Then came Jupiter,
（天文学家）卡西尼发现了这里的大红斑，
where Cassini saw raging storms,
距今已经过去几个世纪了
some centuries old.
卡西尼号还与久负盛名的伽利略号宇宙飞船合作
Cassini also teamed up with the venerable Galileo spacecraft
联合测量木星的磁层，
to jointly measure Jupiter's magnetosphere,
带电粒子的气泡被约束在
a bubble of charged particles trapped*
行星的磁场中
within the planet's magnetic field.
在最近的一次飞抵中，卡西尼号拍摄了这张照片
At closest approach, Cassini took this image.
那时，我们看到了木星最详细的景象
At that time, the most detailed view of Jupiter ever seen.
和木星的相遇是一次全面的彩排
The Jupiter encounter served as a full dress rehearsal
一切都为土星准备
for what awaited at Saturn.
这暴露了不足之处：
It revealed there was work to be done
卡西尼号在设计上有妥协
in addressing Cassini's design compromise.
缺少了扫描平台
The lack of the scan platform that would have allowed
就不能同时使用
simultaneous use of science instruments,
需要移动和需要静止的科学仪器
needing either to move or to be rock steady.
这意味着每次想把仪器对准某处
- It meant you had to turn the spacecraft
都必须旋转整个飞船
every time you wanted to point an instrument someplace.
我们有12种仪器，
And we had 12 instruments,
而且每种仪器一般都有需求
and each instrument generally had
就算不是严格的快速指向要求
different pointing druthers, if not in fact,
也需要不同的指向选择
hard and fast pointing requirements.
于是在不同的科学团队之间
And so there was an awful lot of negotiation
进行了大量的交涉
that went on between the different science teams,
仪器负责人们相互谈判，
the different instrument representatives,
决定出谁有权控制
in deciding who was gonna get to control
飞船的指向
the pointing of the spacecraft when.
经过很长时间，多次谈判，
It took a lot of time, a lot of negotiating,
为了让项目运转，我们做出了很多妥协
a lot of compromises to make that work.
尽管有着如此限制，
- [Narrator] Despite this restraint,
卡西尼号现在可以自豪地说
Cassini could now boast of being the most capable
自己是人类向太阳系发射的
interplanetary spacecraft ever sent out
功能最强大的飞船
into the solar system.
土星轨道插入
经过近七年的旅程，
After a journey of nearly seven years,
卡西尼-惠更斯号探测器和土星已经近在咫尺
Cassini and the Huygens probe are nearing Saturn's doorstep.
二十年的梦想，规划，
Whether two decades of dreaming, planning,
建设和承担这一艰巨的旅行的工作
building, and undertaking this arduous journey
是否能得到回报，即将见分晓
will be rewarded, will soon be known.
因为卡西尼号
For just ahead is the most dangerous moment
即将面临最危险的时刻
that Cassini will face.
SOI
SOI.
土星轨道插入
Saturn Orbit Insertion.
这一刻，没有人比查尔斯·埃拉奇
No one is more excited, or anxious, about this moment
更加激动和焦虑
than Charles Elachi.
除了担任卡西尼号的
In addition to still being the team lead
的雷达实验团队的领导外，
for Cassini's radar experiment,
现在他还主管 JPL
he now heads JPL.
卡西尼号可能是美国承办的
- Cassini is probably one of the most exciting missions
最令人兴奋的任务之一，它值得更多的赞扬
ever undertaken by the US and it deserves more credit.
所以当我们进入轨道插入阶段，
So when we come to the orbit insertion,
经过之前的提议，游说，
after advocating for it, selling it,
建造，飞行阶段
building it and flying it,
现在该打起精神了
it was a really very sobering moment.
引擎最好能点火，否则我们会以飞掠告终
The engine better fire, otherwise we'll end with a fly by.
必须记住火星观察者号的前车之鉴，
You have to remember that we had the Mars Observer,
当我们打开引擎时，飞船就不见了
where when we turned on the engine, the thing disappeared.
11年前，
- [Narrator] 11 years before,
当火星观察者号接近火星时，
as Mars Observer was approaching Mars,
飞船被命令
the spacecraft was commanded to pressurize
给推进系统加压
its propulsion system.
那艘宇宙飞船再也没有音讯了
The spacecraft was never heard from again.
据说是燃料管发生了严重断裂，
It's believed a massive rupture in the fuel lines occurred,
使宇宙飞船处于无法恢复的旋转状态
putting the spacecraft into an unrecoverable spin.
我们大约有15到20分钟的时间
We have about 15, 20 minutes.
这是鲍勃·米切尔，他是项目经理
This is Bob Mitchell, who is the project manager.
好吧，好吧，我想我们已经知道了
- Okay, well, I think we've got what'll be
今晚这里会有一个
a rather interesting program laid out here
相当有趣的节目
for you this evening.
当然会包含一点戏剧性
Certainly gonna have a little drama to it.
我对此相当自信，但还是有些担心
I was kinda confident, but I was worried, concerned.
“紧张”可能是最好的形容
Nervous might be the best word as well.
需要降低速度
- [Narrator] To slow down enough to be captured
才能被土星的引力捕获，
by Saturn's gravity,
卡西尼号必须要启动不常用的引擎
Cassini will have to turn on its seldom used engine
共计96分钟
for 96 minutes.
低于这个时间就会飞过这个星球，
Anything less could result in flying past the planet,
一去不返
never to return.
飞行路线将引导卡西尼号和探测器
The flight path will take Cassini and the probe
在土星光环的缝隙中上下穿梭
up through and back down a gap in Saturn's rings.
人们担心在这些区域
There's worry that there could be particles
可能会有粒子造成破坏
in these regions large enough to damage,
甚至摧毁飞船
or even destroy, the spacecraft.
作为一名光环科学家，
- I think as a ring scientist,
我最关心的是如何穿越这个
my greatest concern was really crossing through that gap
F环和G环之间的缝隙
in the F and G rings.
只要一个弹珠大小的颗粒
It would only have taken one marble sized particle
撞上飞船的关键位置
in the wrong place in the spacecraft
大概任务就可以宣告结束了
to perhaps have ended the mission.
所以对我来说，最惊险的
So for me, the most, you know, breathtaking,
心跳停止的时刻
the heart stopping time, was really
就是穿过土星环平面的时候
crossing through the ring plane.
为了降低风险，
- [Narrator] To reduce the risk,
卡西尼号将用它的高增益天线指向前方
Cassini will fly through the gaps with its high gain antenna
充当穿越缝隙时的盾牌
facing forward to act as a shield.
在这些时间里，唯一能返回地球的
During these times, the only signal coming back to Earth
将是从较小的天线发射出的单一频率信号
will be from a smaller antenna transmitting a single tone.
信号的波长或频率
The pitch, or frequency, of the tone will vary
随着飞船速度的变化会有所不同
with changes to the spacecraft's speed.
这就是多普勒效应
What's known as the Doppler effect.
这将告诉工程师飞船运行正常
This will tell engineers how the spacecraft is performing...
还是失控
or not.
-零是参考频率，
- Zero is the reference frequency,
如果引擎点火失败，
the nominal frequency that we would see
我们将看到这个标准频率
if there were no burn.
所以如果发动机没有点火，
So if the motor never ignited,
这张图上将会显示
what would happen is this line up here
一条横向的直线
would just go right straight across.
所以入夜时，我躺在床上想着：
I would lie in bed at night and think about
我们还应该做哪些测试？
what other tests should we do?
我还应该问什么问题？
What other question should I be asking?
还需要查出哪些未完成的事项？
What should we be poking at here that we haven't done yet?
这里的这个尖角对应于
And this corner right here corresponds to
点火结束的时刻
where the burn should end.
我不可能知晓
There wasn't any single thing that I could point to
哪些特定的事情
and say that thing right there
将要出差错
has a fair chance of biting us.*
这根本就不可能做到
There just wasn't anything like that.
但是你必须考虑所有预期的情况…
But when you consider all the things that had to happen...
以及非预期的情况，
or not happen,
需要考量的条件太多
there were enough of them that the aggregate of them
足以让人焦虑
was cause for being nervous.
我正是如此
And I was.
这时就要引起关注了
That would be cause for some level of concern.
SOI是一项团队工作
- [Julie] SOI was such a, just such a team effort.
我们追查一切可能出错的事情
We chased everything that could go wrong
这非常困难
down the rabbit hole.
我们考虑每一种情况，如果这里出了问题，
We went down every path of, if this goes wrong,
我们该怎么办？
what do we do?
如果那里又出现问题，我们该怎么办？
If that goes wrong, what do we do?
共运行了10000个用例来测试轨道插入
There were 10,000 tests run to put together that insertion.
这是我们一直在准备的东西
- Something we've been preparing for
经过了四五年的不断测试，
for four or five years, testing and testing,
包括各种可能的极端情况
awfulizing all of the possible things that could go wrong.
这是就是关键时刻之一
And this was one of those moments where you're either
要么进入轨道，要么数十亿美元打水漂
in orbit or you're a billion dollar fly by.
卡西尼号任务控制中心状况良好
- Things continue to go well in Cassini mission control.
离点火开始还有约33分钟
We're approximately 33 minutes from burn start.
这是我们的飞行总监朱莉·韦伯斯特
There's our flight director, Julie Webster.
这位是我们今晚不希望听到发言的人：
This is one person we hope to not hear from tonight.
系统故障保护工程师Paula Morgan
This is system fault protection engineer, Paula Morgan.
如果我们收到故障保护信息，
And if we hear from fault protection,
这意味着我们在飞船上发现了某种异常情况
that means we've had some sort of anomaly on the spacecraft.
道格·约翰逊，我们的无线电科学和SOI通讯员
Doug Johnson, our radio science and SOI communicator.
今晚我们将从他那里通过多普勒信号
He's the one reporting most of the events we'll see tonight
收到大部分事件的播报
through that Doppler signal.
控制台上的简·伯克利
- [Narrator] Also on console is Jan Berkeley.
最初在JPL工作时是一名大学实习生
She first worked at JPL as a college intern.
现在她是卡西尼小组的关键成员
Now she's a key member of the Cassini team
负责创建计算机指令序列
that creates the computer sequence commands
来操纵飞船
that operate the spacecraft.
我们会运行指令，
- We would run them, make sure that there were
确保程序没有问题
no problems with that.
如果需要做测试，我们会安排
If we needed to do testing, we would schedule testing.
我们才是真正把命令送到宇宙飞船的人
We were the ones that actually sent them to the spacecraft.
然后等待指令生效
And then we watched them clock out.*
最紧张的时刻不是按下发送按钮，
That was the tense moment, was not pushing the button,
而是等待它传回生效的信息
it was waiting for it to come back, that it worked.
而土星离我们太远了，光是信号的往返时间
And Saturn was so far away that it would take three hours
就需要三个小时
just to get there and come back.
卡西尼号航天器的当前速度：
- Current speed of the Cassini spacecraft:
每秒22.2公里，
22.2 kilometers per second,
每小时不到50000英里
which is just under 50,000 miles an hour.
随着土星的引力增长，速度还在增加
And increasing as Saturn's gravity draws us in.
那是Shin Huh，我们的SOI系统工程师
That's Shin Huh, our SOI systems engineer.
他日日夜夜研究 SOI
Shin has eaten, breathed, slept, and lived SOI
已有多年
for many years.
今晚是他的关键时刻
Tonight is his big night.
SOI系统上的所有岗位
- All stations on that SOI systems.
只是提醒一下，我们即将准时到达
Just an advisory, we're coming up on the time
因为关键的
for the critical sequence will initiate the turn
SOI 点火姿态序列将要启动
to the SOI burn attitude.
点火命令将在当地时间下午7:35:35发送
The burn command will be sent at 7:35:35 PM local time.
SOI系统飞行总监，
Flight director, SOI systems,
所有子系统报告航天器参数达标
all subsystems report the spacecraft data is nominal
并准备支持进行SOI
and ready to support SOI.
好的，我知道了
- [Man] Okay, I copy that.
SOI，飞行通信总监
SOI, comms flight director...
我们待命中
- [Todd] We're waiting.
复制通信
- Copy telecomm*
JPL的传统活动
A JPL tradition has begun,
从任务支援区后方开始
starting in the back of the Mission Support Area.
这是JPL的幸运花生时间
This is the consuming of the lucky JPL peanuts.
道格·约翰逊刚刚报告了一个信号，
Doug Johnson just reported a signal,
我们在穿越土星环时幸存了下来
we've survived the ring plane crossing
已经通过F环和G环
through the F and G rings.
一波未平一波又起，
One hurdle down, one to go, with the start of the burn*
引擎将在9分钟后点火
a meer nine minutes away.
FSL 的飞行总监
- [Julie] ACE flight director on FSL court.
你还在B2频道追踪堪培拉(CDSCC)吗？
Are you still tracking Canberra on B2?
是的
- [Man] That's affirmative.
继续，把堪培拉切换到B-Zero
- Let's go ahead and switch Canberra over to B-Zero.
继续，导航一号
Go ahead, NAV-1.
我们可以确认收到了
- [Man] We can confirm that we are receiving
来自DSN的单向数据
one way data from the DSN.
DSS14的单向多普勒？
- [Julie] One way Doppler from DSS14?
是的
- [Man] Yes, that's affirmative.
导航也可以确认收到了
- Navigation can also confirm we're receiving
多普勒数据
the Doppler data.
我们已经证实了这个
We've been able to verify that the turn
转向 SY-burn 的姿态已经完成
to the SY burn attitude is complete.*
离SOI点火还有两分钟
We're approaching two minutes before the SOI burn.
成千上万科学家和工程师们的希望和梦想
Hopes and dreams of thousands of scientists
将静待接下来的几分钟的结局
and engineers are resting on the next few moments.
祝你好运，卡西尼惠更斯号
So Godspeed, Cassini Huygens.
期望能在轨道上看到你
May we see you in orbit.
我们要去看看
- We're gonna drop in.
在多普勒显示上，我们预期的是
- On the Doppler display, what we're looking for
沿着那条线
is a turning of the corner to start to follow that line
折向右下角
down to the lower right.
这就是点火开始的迹象
And that's our indication the burn has begun.
飞行控制，这里是SOI通信..
Flight, SOI comms..
说吧
- [Julie] Go ahead.
我们收到了
- [Man] We have a Doppler signature consistent
引擎点火的多普勒信号
with engine turn on.
任务控制中心
- [Todd] Lots of high fives and celebrations
都在击掌和庆祝
in mission control.
祝贺为了此刻
Congratulations all of you that have worked so hard
所有辛勤工作的人
for this moment.
已经过了一分钟，总计需要96分钟
One minute down, about 96 minutes to go.
我们将继续沿着预期曲线
We're continuing to follow the nominal predicted curve
在多普勒图上行进
on the Doppler.
所以事实上我们已经经过拐角
So the fact we turned the corner
表示引擎已启动
means the engine has started.
事实上，我们正在遵循这条路线
The fact that we're following the line
意味着我们从引擎中获得了正确的推力
means we're getting the right thrust out of the engine.
卡西尼-惠更斯号飞船还将传来更多的好消息
So more good news for the Cassini Huygens spacecraft.
-干得好
- Way to go.
干得好
Way to go.
-现在需要经过90分钟的等待
- [Narrator] There's now 90 minutes of waiting
直到卡西尼号的引擎停止工作
until Cassini's engine is to stop firing.
行动的空当提供了一个难得的机会
The lull in the action affords a rare opportunity
给在场的国会议员
to give members of Congress who are on hand
提供一次非常近距离的私人参观机会
a very up close and personal tour.
这是见证历史的时刻，
It's a moment to witness history in the making,
正如政治家们深知的，
and, as politicians well-know,
需要利用优秀的摄影作品来记录
to take advantage of an excellent photo op.
NASA 卡西尼号任务控制中心，现在是晚上7点42分
- It's 7:42 PM in NASA's Cassini mission control.
接下来我们预期在 A 环发生“掩星”现象
The next thing we'll look for is an occultation
太平洋时间当地时间晚上8点05分左右
by the A ring around 8:05 PM Pacific time local.
那时，在多普勒信号中
At that time, we'll see an increased noise
我们会看到噪音增加，
in the Doppler signal,
与多普勒图最左边部分
similar to the increased noise there at the far left
增加的噪音类似
of the Doppler plot.
还有今晚最后的惊悚时刻：
And our final scary moment of the evening
需要确保引擎停止燃烧
will be to make sure to get the burn shut down.
这将是为JPL、NASA和全世界创造历史的一天
The history making day for JPL, NASA, and the world.
飞行控制，SOI通信
- [Man] Flight, SOI comm.
-继续，SOI通信
- Go ahead, SOI comm.
我们正好通过了A环
- [Man] We have hit the A ring pretty hard.*
-好的
- All right.
SOI 通信那边有更多好消息，
- [Todd] More good news from SOI Comm there,
我们的多普勒数据图上发生了可怕的变化
the frightening looking change to our Doppler data
但这完全是意料之中的事
is totally anticipated.
这证明了土星的A环与预期一致
This proves that Saturn's A ring is where we think it is.
卡西尼号飞船也同样尽在掌握
And the Cassini spacecraft is where we think it is as well.
我们继续跟踪2到3分贝的信号
- [Man] We're continuing to track a two to three DB signal
通过A环时偶尔会中断
with occasional outages through the A ring.
我们希望看到一个很清晰的强烈信号，
And we expect to see a nice strong signal,
我们马上就要到关键部分了
we have the main division coming up.
收到，听起来不错
- [Julie] Copy that, sounds good.
我们看到，飞船正在接近B环，
- [Todd] As we see, we're approaching the B ring,
必须记住今晚我们看见的这一切
and we must remember tonight, everything happening at Saturn
都发生在一小时24分钟之前
occurred an hour and 24 minutes earlier
都怪那讨厌的每秒186000英里的光速，
due to that pesky speed of light, 186,000 miles per second,
限制了我们的星际通信速度
our interplanetary speed limit, if you will.
SOI通信，继续
- [Julie] Go ahead SOI Comm.
在达到11分贝的短暂峰值后，
- [Man] After a brief peak up to 11DB,
我们现在已离开该部分
we have now exited the division.
-收到
- Copy.
刚才发生了什么事？
- [Man] What just happened?
他们刚刚宣布我们现在
- They just announced that we are now
已经被土星捕获
a captured object around Saturn.
我们现在是一个轨道...轨道飞行器
We are now an orbit... an orbiter.
历史上第一个土星轨道飞行器
- First in history around Saturn.
如你所见
- There you go.
第一个环绕土星的人造轨道飞行器
First man-made orbiter around Saturn.
旅行者号，羡慕吧
Voyager, eat your heart out.
SOI系统，这是意外事件
- [Man] SOI systems, this is contingency.
还有两分钟多一点就要到达最接近点
- Closest approach is just a little over two minutes away.
考虑到这一点，可能是时候开始
And given that, it's probably about time
我们的土星天气预报
for our Saturnian weather forecast.
预测今天的气温为-226华氏度
Predicted temps today, -226 degrees Fahrenheit
或-143摄氏度
or -143 degrees Celsius.
风速每小时1100英里左右
Winds of 1100 miles per hour or so.
内部出现氦雨的可能性为100%
Chance of helium rain inside the interior, 100%.
还会有地球大小的飓风
Hurricanes the size of the Earth.
卡西尼号最好把舱门关上
Cassini would do well to batten down the hatches.
正以极快的速度进行最近的一次抵近
Closest approach is upon us with a speed
速度几乎达到每小时69000英里
of almost 69,000 miles per hour.
而且已经开始减速
And the speed HAS started slowing.
飞行控制，这里是SOI通讯
- [Man] Flight, SOI Comm.
请说，SOI通讯
- [Julie] Go ahead, SOI Comm.
多普勒图已经变平了
- [Man] The Doppler has flattened out.
好的，用于SOI的引擎
- [Todd] Okay, we have burn complete here,
已经停止燃烧了
for the SOI orbit insertion burn.
任务控制中心都在祝贺
Congratulations continue in mission control.
击掌声从后面的
The high-fives begin in the back
任务支援区传来
of our mission support area.
我刚从无线电里听到消息...
I'm just hearing a report from radio...
-你做得很好
- You did great.
你做得很好非常感谢
You did great. - Thank you.
-不客气
- My pleasure.
为我们幸运的推进工程师们干杯
Here's to our lucky propulsion engineers.
今晚的工作非常出色
Did a wonderful job tonight.
-知道它幸存了下来
- Knowing that it survived and was there
我们已经准备好了
and we were ready to, you know,
开始进入科学部分，获取伟大的图像
get to the meat of the science and get these great images.
那是一个美妙的时刻
It was a wonderful moment.
旅程开始了
The voyage begins.
我们成功了，我们做到了
We made it, like, we did it.
-干得好
- Fantastic job.
现在我们要把你的ECAP纳入考核
- Now we're gonna put your ECAP in.
我的领导刚刚通知我，
- [Todd] I was just informed by my management,
她会把我的绩效评估纳入考核
she'll put my performance evaluation in.
我很高兴她等到今晚成功后才这么做
I'm glad she waited until our success tonight.
它活下来了
It's alive.
- It's alive.
土星环
先是一场狂欢
- So there's this amazing elation
紧接着就沉寂下来，
and then almost immediately a crash,
因为我们都精疲力竭
just because we're exhausted and tired,
但是我睡不着
but I couldn't sleep.
所以我留在了MSA，
And so I stayed in the MSA,
光环的图像在回放，
and the images of the rings were playing back,
慢慢地，人们开始聚集在这些图像周围，
and slowly people started to gather around these images,
这些在飞过光环的顶端时拍摄的特写镜头
which no one had seen close up images
之前从未有人见过
flying right over the tops of the rings.
我只觉得心潮起伏
And there were just goosebumps.
那是我永远难忘的记忆
That's a memory I will never forget.
这是更多的小环，小片
- This is way more ringlets, little pieces.
到目前为止，任务主要是
- [Narrator] Until now, the mission has been
工程师的领域
mostly the province of engineers.
从这些土星光环的第一张特写照片开始，
With these first ever closeup images of Saturn's rings,
项目郑重地转向科学领域
the shift to science begins in earnest,
从已知情况来看，
and there are hints of major discoveries ahead
未来还有重大发现的迹象
from what already can be seen.
我认为即使不是一个光环科学家
- I don't think you have to be a ring scientist
也能理解昨晚对我们来说意味着什么
to imagine what last night was for us.
真是无以言表
It was beyond description really.
真是震撼心灵
It was mind blowing.
这是你能想到的所有形容词
It was every adjective you could think of.
它的美丽完全超出我的预期
I'm surprised at how surprised I am at the beauty
图像的清晰度也令人惊喜
and the clarity of these images.
真是叹为观止
They are shocking to me.
飞船为我们提供了一个非常稳定的平台
The spacecraft allows us a very steady platform.
这台机器的指向很稳定
This machine, you turn it, you point it, and it stays there.
它就像太空中的三脚架
It's like a tripod in space.
无论如何，我想光环科学家们会忙上一阵了
Anyway, I think ring scientists are gonna have a field day.
谢谢你
So thank you.
哇！
Wow.
卡西尼号的到来恰逢其时
- [Narrator] Cassini's arrival coincided
有一段时间土星的光照角度很好，
with a time when the planet was well lit by sunlight,
展现了光环的非凡景色
providing extraordinary views of the rings.
土星加上土星环的宽度约为25万英里，
Saturn, plus the rings, span about a quarter million miles,
这个宽度和地月距离差不多
and they would fit in between the Earth and its moon.
然而，在这个广阔区域中，
And yet for all of its wide expanse,
光环本身非常薄，
the rings themselves are paper thin,
只有大约10英尺厚
only about 10 feet thick.
如果你能收集到所有的环粒子，
If you could scoop up all the ring particles,
它的质量会比土星的
there would be less mass than one of Saturn's
小卫星Mimas的质量还小
small moons named Mimas.
从远处看，
- [Narrator] From a distance,
光环散发出一种宁静的感觉，
the rings cast off a sense of serenity,
但它们既美丽又复杂且混乱
but they are as complex and chaotic as they are beautiful.
因为它们是由无数
For they are made up of countless numbers
不同大小和形状的杂乱无章的物体组成的
of disorderly objects of different sizes and shapes.
这是一幅基于雷达观测的模拟图像，
This is a simulated image based on radar observations,
依据光环不同区域的颗粒大小
showing particles sizes found in different regions
显示不同的颜色
of the rings.
紫色代表了当前位置
The color purple represents where there is
主要由小于两英寸的物体构成
a preponderance of objects smaller than two inches.
绿色区域的颗粒大小约为一英寸
Particles in green are about an inch in size.
蓝色条纹的颗粒更小
The blueish bands are still smaller.
白色条带是颗粒密集区域
The white bands are dense regions that radio signals
无线电信号无法穿透
were unable to penetrate.
此伪彩色图像突出显示了
This false color image highlights what can be seen
紫外线下可以看到的物体
in the ultraviolet.
绿松石色代表水冰
The turquoise colors represent water ice.
红色是一种不同的粒子
The red colors are a different kind of particle.
无法确定它的成分，
Uncertain as to what it might be,
于是科学家们决定把它命名为尘土
the scientists decided to name it dirt.
卡西尼号也能够测量
- Cassini was also able to measure
环中粒子的温度，
the temperature of the ring particles,
那些有较多尘土和黑点的光环
and the rings that had the most dirt or pollution*
比明亮的冰环温度稍微高一点
were slightly warmer than the bright icy rings.
尽管主要由
- [Narrator] And, despite being made of
宇宙尘埃和冰组成，
mostly cosmic dust and ice,
这些圆环中也包含一些像房子一样大的结构
the rings contained some structures as large as a house.
科学家们惊奇地发现，
And as scientists discovered to their astonishment,
甚至短暂地出现过“山脉”
even transitory mountains.
卡西尼号任务有一个独特的时刻
- There is a unique moment in the Cassini mission
那时阳光从环的边缘平行射入，
where the sun was edge onto the rings,
这让我们可以看到10英尺厚的圆环上下
and that allowed us to see anything that would stick up
任何凸起的东西
above or below those 10 feet thick rings.
看哪，我们找到了像是山脉的物体
Then lo and behold, we found what looked like mountains
在光环上投下巨大的阴影
casting huge shadows on the rings.
结果证明土星的光环
And it turns out that the rings of Saturn
不仅仅是独立的粒子，
are not like just individual particles,
还有很多粒子粘在一起
but a lot of these particles stick together
并成长为越来越大的颗粒
and grow into larger and larger particles.
但这些粒子团是短暂的
But these clumps of particles are ephemeral.
它们不会持续很长时间
They don't last for a long time.
它们可以分裂，然后重组成新的颗粒
They can be broken up and then reformed in to new particles.
土星的卫星和小卫星
- [Narrator] Saturn's moons and smaller moonlets
也影响了光环
also influenced the rings.
即使是轨道上的碎石堆也会摆动
Even orbiting rubble piles hold a kind of sway.*
总之，它们为土星的光环
Altogether, they help shape the boundaries
塑造边界
of Saturn's rings,
也聚集了粒子
herding in particles that might otherwise
否则这些颗粒要么坠入土星
rain down in a torrent on the planet
要么逃逸到深空
or escape into deep space.
与此同时，一些颗粒
Meanwhile, particles from some of Saturn's moons
从土星的卫星上不断剥离，
are constantly shedding off,
帮助保持现有的环或创造出新的环
helping to preserve existing rings or creating new ones.
在环内的意外发现
Among the unexpected discoveries within the rings
是这些类似螺旋桨的物体
were these propeller like objects.
螺旋桨结构是这些最大的环状粒子团，
- Propellers are these largest clumps of ring particles,
它们变得足够大，所以它们的重力
and they get big enough so their gravity
想要推开环，打开一个缝隙
wants to push apart the rings and open up a gap.
但后来没有足够的重力
And then there's not quite enough gravity
一路打开缺口
to open it up all the way.
你看到这些小螺旋桨了吗
And so you see these little propellers
分布在光环上，
sprinkled throughout the rings,
尤其是土星的A环
especially in Saturn's A ring.
有一个可以追溯到旅行者号的谜团
- [Narrator] A mystery dating back to Voyager
是幽灵般出现和消失的辐条
was the appearing and disappearing of ghostly spokes.
卡西尼号确定了原因
Cassini determined their cause.
静电能使尘埃颗粒上升，
Electrostatic charges that lift up dust particles,
因此可以在指环之上漂浮一段时间
where they levitate for a time above the rings.
还有两个根本问题
There remain two fundamental questions
没有明确的答案
lacking definitive answers.
首先是光环如何形成
The first is knowing how the rings came to be.
关于光环的许多事情至今仍无法解释
- So many things about the rings are unexplained even now.
关于土星光环最初是如何形成的，
There are a lot of ideas for how Saturn's rings
众说纷纭
initially formed.
其中一个原因可能是这些环
One of those is that perhaps the rings formed
是在土星形成的时候
from the material that was left over
由剩余的材料组成的
from when Saturn formed.
如果这是真的，那么光环是本来就有的，
So if that's true, then the rings are old,
和土星本身一样古老
as old as Saturn itself.
其他想法是：假设有一个物体，可能是彗星，
Other ideas: say perhaps an object may be a comet,
或者是一颗流星，离土星太近了，
or a meteor, came in too close to Saturn,
被土星的引力撕裂，
was torn apart by Saturn's gravity,
然后创造了光环
and then created the rings.
或者是一个卫星离土星太近了
Or perhaps a moon wandered too close to Saturn
被土星撕碎
and was torn apart.
因此，光环可能只有
And so then the rings could be as young as maybe only 10
1000万或者一亿年的历史
or a hundred million years old.
除了确定光环的起源，
- [Narrator] Along with determining the origin of the rings,
光环的结局也是一个悬而未决的问题
understanding their fate is also an unanswered question.
有句格言是：没有什么是永恒的
But the adage that nothing lasts forever
可能也适用于土星环
likely applies even to them.
随着微流星体继续轰击光环，
- As micro meteoroids continue to bombard the rings,
一些最里面的粒子落入土星
and some of the innermost particles fall into Saturn
成为它的一部分，
and actually water* the planet,
随着时间的推移，光环颜色会越来越浅
the rings are getting lighter and lighter with time.
也许再过几亿年，
And so perhaps in another few hundred million years,
我们所知道的土星环可能已经消失了
Saturn's rings as we know it might be gone.
也许会留下一个狭窄的环
Maybe we'll be left with narrow rings
就像我们在天王星系统看到的那样
like we see in the Uranus system.
很久之后的某天，
- [Narrator] And one day long from now,
土星光环可能会完全消失
Saturn's glorious rings might disappear altogether.
我们现在欣赏土星环的理由又多了一个
One more reason to enjoy them while we can.
下次的“JPL与太空时代”节目中，
Next time on "JPL and the Space Age",
“土星上的胜利”的第二部分...
Part Two of "Triumph at Saturn"...
卡西尼号安全进入轨道，科学任务占据主导地位，
With Cassini safely in orbit, science takes center stage,
以及惠更斯探测器激动人心的
beginning with the dramatic descent of the Huygens Probe
降落到土卫六表面的过程
to the surface of Saturn's moon Titan.
我们知道泰坦是个很难对付的目标，
- [Man] We knew Titan was a tough target,
他恪守自己的秘密
was going to hold its secrets tightly.
所以我们设计了这个任务来揭开它
And so we designed this mission to hit it
尽我们所能
with everything we've got.
在接下来的几年里，
- [Narrator] In the years that follow,
将会取得一个又一个意想不到的发现，
one unexpected discovery after another will be made,
为这项国际任务
earning this international mission
赢得来自世界各地的赞誉
accolades from around the world.
科学是注重发现，
- Science is about what is,
而工程学关注实现
and engineering is about what can BE.
卡西尼-惠更斯计划
The Cassini-Huygens program has demonstrated
就是两者结合的最佳典范
the best of both.
新发现的数量
The number of your new discoveries
简直令人欣喜若狂
is nothing short of amazing.
我想说卡西尼号的发现
- [Woman] I would say Cassini's discoveries
从根本上改变了我们看待太阳系的方式
fundamentally altered the way we look at our solar system.
在一颗行星周围，我们发现了两颗卫星
Around one planet, we find two moons
它们有潜在的宜居条件，
that could potentially be habitable,
而且具有支持生命存在的关键成分
have the key ingredients to support life.
我对土星及其卫星
- I have more than a passing interest in Saturn
热情不减
and its family of moons.
卡西尼号发射时，我们只知道18颗卫星
When Cassini was launched, we knew only 18 moons.
现在已经发现60个，而且还在增加
I understand there's now 60 and counting.
我忍不住要说，
I can't resist the temptation to say,
天哪，竟存在如此之多的卫星
my God, it's full of moons.
“土星上的胜利”第二部分，且听下回分解
- [Narrator] "Triumph at Saturn" Part Two, next time.